Stanford University you think I don't
know don't you know as a matter of fact
I do know and this what we're going to
talk about tonight and it's called the
phenomena what is it
pigs pigs thank you you started to cover
this last week and I didn't really you
describe what you were talking about is
giving mass to the photon yes that's
what we're going to talk about tonight
we don't actually give mass the photon
so what no no that's that's right that's
right the real photon the symmetry group
associated with it is not spontaneously
broken tonight we're going to talk about
how if the symmetry group associated
with the photon were broken
spontaneously how it would give the
photon of mass now the reason we're
doing that is because exactly that
phenomena happens with the Z boson and
the W bosons the photon is or
the photon is a little bit simpler
indeed it might have had a mass the fact
that it doesn't have a mass is perhaps
an accident of nature the absence of an
appropriate Higgs field we're going to
talk about what the Higgs field is to
give it mass so that's what we want to
talk about tonight
how gauge bosons like the photon get a
mass when spontaneous symmetry breaking
what is the symmetry incidentally when I
say you associated with the photon
there's a conserved quantity which is
the charge conserved quantities always
go with symmetries what's the symmetry
that's connected with the conservation
of electric charge you want it's the
thing which multiplies the charged
fields by a phase it is a kind of
rotation in the complex plane the
complex field so I'm going to explain to
you tonight how spontaneous symmetry
breaking of that symmetry
induces a mass for the photon now there
is a situation in nature where the
photon does get a mass and the symmetry
of you on symmetry is spontaneously
broken does anybody know what it is well
it is a kinetics condensed matter yes
okay the answer is in a superconductor
in a superconductor photons propagate
with a mass now that's in the
superconductor when they leave the
superconductor their photons again when
they're in the superconductor they
behave as if they had a mass okay so
that's an example of the Higgs phenomena
or and we can talk about it yeah that'd
also be the case when the photon is
travelling through something present a
vacuum well the super conductivity only
happens when the photon is traveling
through something other than the vacuum
no no super conductivity or the photon
no no no the photon does not propagate
with a mass in a prism its velocity is
slower than the speed of light but it's
still true that at zero momentum meaning
infinite wavelength its frequency is
zero okay let's talk about the
difference that's an interesting
difference might as well talk about it
the relevant issue is the shape of a
certain curve the curve is
either energy versus momentum or for
waves what corresponds to momentum for
waves either inverse wavelength or wave
number K everybody remember K K is
basically the inverse of the wavelength
and vertically what we have instead of
energy now the K is like P vertical here
was energy frequency frequency Omega
alright remember e equals H bar Omega
and P equals H Bar K all right so K is
wave number the number of waves that fit
into a given into a unit the distance
all right so this these two planes are
the same except for a fact of H bar all
right what is what is Omega versus K
look like for an electromagnetic wave in
empty space well what's the connection
between Omega and K Omega equals C times
K that's it Omega equals C times K now
the same relationship incidentally is
true of sound waves waves on a long
string and so forth approximately the
same relationship the difference of
course is they have different velocities
of propagation but notice that Omega is
zero when K is zero that means on this
side over here that the energy is of a
quantum or light or wave the energy is
zero when the momentum is zero what do
we call a particle when its energy is
zero and then when the energy is zero if
its mass is zero we call it what we call
it photons yes but we call it massless
all right so any wave which has the
property that Omega goes smoothly to
zero as K goes to zero we call massless
and typically the shape
of the curve looks like that taken be
positive and negative corresponding to a
wave going to the left or the right
let's forget going to the left okay
the frequency goes to zero when the
wavelength becomes infinite
that's massless and all that happens in
a prism is that sea changes see changes
okay now what about um what about a
particle with mass for particle of mass
its energy is equal to the square root
of P squared plus M Squared now there's
some C's there I think there's a C to
the fourth and no C squared C squared
nimbala C squared P squared plus M
Squared C to the fourth right but if we
set C equal to 1 it's the square root of
P squared plus M Squared what does that
look like that's a curve which looks
like this it's a hyperbola
in fact if we Square this we get e
squared let's set C squared to one e
squared minus P squared equals M squared
that's a hyperbola you see the
difference in this case when P goes to
zero the energy is not zero that's the
rest mass or just a mass if you like the
rest mass is the value of the energy
when the momentum goes to zero all right
so are two different situations one the
velocity of light may be different in a
prism than it is an empty space but that
just changes the slope of this curve and
does not change the fact that the energy
is zero at the origin here the other
situation is that the energy is not zero
at the origin and has this hyperbolic
shape that's called having a mass and
notice that there's a frequency same
thing here that a wave with infinite
wavelength as
finite frequency what does infinite
wavelength mean it means you disturb the
field every place the same you rigidly
you make the field
absolutely homogeneous homogeneous means
it's everywhere is the same you shift
the field everywhere and you let it go
what happens is everywhere as it starts
to oscillate simultaneously that's the
phenomenon over here infinite wavelength
zero wave vector the whole field
oscillates it also corresponds to
particles at rest
oscillating because they have mass okay
all right so that's what the important
thing to keep in mind is that
oscillations of a field when it's
homogeneous when it has infinite
wavelength those are the things we call
mass as answer the question about the
wave numbers it changes changes it what
was moving through a soft solid right
you can have any way Harper I mean if
you take took away a ray and run it into
it into a piece of glass it's not the
Omegas exchange that's right if you if
you have a wave of a given frequency and
it shines on a piece of glass the
frequency doesn't change when it goes
into the into the into the material but
as I think you're for seeing two
different materials might have a
different slope here so at the same
value of frequency you would jump from
one you could jump from one wave number
to another and that's what happens
this situation where the entire field
shifts would that be equivalent to tae
seop's entanglement Yamuna nor a little
entanglement this is a perfectly
classical wave field and I I understand
that but what I'm saying is entanglement
says that this particle over here and
this particle over here responds
instantaneously and by the entire field
ship and leave that no doubt / no no
entanglement is a situation where you
have two particles in two different
states which are entangled with each
other a over here B over here or a over
here B over here after they have to be
in it has to be two different states
spin up and spin down spin down and spin
up a classical field is when all of the
particles are in the same state it's
quite thick yeah it's all in curve that
you drew but that looks more like PE and
it W what is what does that represent
yeah great this is Corki the
relationship between Omega and K between
frequency and wave number is called the
dispersion relation you say there's no
dispersion when Omega is a linear
function of K when Omega is a linear
incidentally the slope of this curve is
the velocity the Omega decay is a yeah
the Omega DK is the velocity of the wave
okay so if the slope of this is constant
everywhere is then all waves move with
the same velocity
all right that's light always move of
the same delight the same velocity if
the slope varies from place to place for
example as it would if there was a mass
then different wavelengths propagate
with different velocities in that case
the wave will disperse so it's called
the dispersion relation let's let's name
it now Omega the Omega as a function of
K that relationship is called the
dispersion relation of the
so the words go that a massless
expectation is one with a linear
dispersion relation a massive particle
is one with a dispersion relation that
does not go to 0 as K goes to 0 but has
a curvature and shape like that and the
mass is nothing but the energy of the
quantum when the momentum is zero so
that's M energy of a quanta quantum as a
function of the momentum when the
momentum goes to zero is the mass all
right so that's a that's the notion of
mass and it is connected with the
curvature of the potential energy of the
field at the or the curvature of the
potential energy at the equilibrium
point wherever the equilibrium point
happens to be why because if you shift
the field away from the equilibrium
point let's say everywhere is
homogeneous Lea everywhere is the same
what happens is it starts to oscillate
about there it's pulled toward lower
energy and overshoots goes up and goes
back and that corresponds to Omega not
being zero at k equals zero K equals
zero means you shift the field
everywhere simultaneously homogeneous
lee all right so we take the field and
we shift it everywhere simultaneously
and the frequency at that point is the
mass if the frequency is zero and the
only way the frequency will be zero is
if the potential energy is flat as a
function of the field if the potential
energy happens to be flat and you shift
the field away from the minimum here
it's not a minimum anymore it's just a
flat directions called a flat direction
of all things it's called a flat
direction if you shift the field along a
flat direction it won't respond it will
just sit there so that corresponds to
the homogeneous field K equals zero
having no energy no frequency
frequency zero all right so you spot a
massless object when there's a direction
a flat direction of the potential here
the flat direction of the potential is
going around the rim on the other hand
if you excite the field perpendicular to
that it oscillates and so this pretend
this kind of field has two distinct
kinds of quanta associated with it
one massless one mass massive what's the
mass of one called in the context of the
standard model incidentally massive the
Higgs boson okay so oscillating this way
we would call the Higgs boson and it has
a mass what about oscillating this way
that's the Goldstone boson its massless
but there is no massless Goldstone boson
in nature so something happened to it
and the parlance of high energy physics
the Goldstone boson got eaten by the
gauge boson resulting in giving the
Higgs boson a mass so that's the
phenomenon that we want to do
mathematically tonight the Goldstone
boson eaten by the gauge boson resulting
in a mass for the Higgs boson okay
remember the Goldstone boson is the one
associated with a motion around here the
Higgs boson is the one associated with
us over here okay so let's let's go
through it there's mathematics to this
if I could do it without mathematics I
would but I can't so we're going to do
it with mathematics and we've already
set up the ingredients we've already set
up the basic ingredients for it all we
have to do is combine them together
so that means in a standard bottle
there's only one spontaneous symmetry
breaking and that's the Higgs field no
it's not a simple you one symmetry it's
this su 2 symmetry of the weak
interactions that take ups to downs and
neutrinos to throw electrons so it's a
little more intricate than just the u 1
symmetry breaking the gauge was getting
mass to everything including yourself
including itself yeah yes well no no no
no no yes and no yes or no okay so let's
let me tell you what the point is there
are a collection of particles in the
standard model which for one
mathematical reason or another cannot
have any mass unless the symmetry is
spontaneously broken now we're going to
go through those regions or reasons
we're going to go through them for
various particles and see what the
reasons are why mass is disallowed by
the standard model without spontaneous
symmetry breaking
then when spontaneous symmetry breaking
happens all of those particles get mass
and they become the masses of the
standard of the standard model particles
they might ask why what about particles
it didn't require a spontaneous symmetry
breaking to get a mass are there any
particles that don't require a
spontaneous symmetry breaking to get a
mass and the answer is yes they can be
those particles are all the particles
that we don't see in the laboratory why
would it be that we would see those
which symmetry breaking gives a mass and
we don't see those
that symmetry breaking doesn't give a
mass any any speculations of why why
that might be yeah yeah yeah the natural
mass might be way up at the Planck scale
the natural masses of particles may be
very much larger leaving over a bunch of
particles which don't have masses for
what you're calling natural reasons and
those particles only get mass from
spontaneous symmetry breaking those
particles are the light ones those are
the ones we see in the laboratory we
have every reason to believe and in fact
I think we practically know by now
that there are additional particles in
nature for example the dark matter
particles we don't know with absolute
certainty what the dark matter particles
are but it seems very likely that the
dark particle dark matter particles are
particles a thousand times heavier than
a proton for example why is it that
those particles have large mass and the
other ones don't and the answer is in
the mathematics of the theory those
particles which have large mass don't
require the phenomena of spontaneous
symmetry breaking to get a mass so we're
going to go through that that's my goal
for tonight and if we don't make it
through it entirely next time the Higgs
phenomena and what the words mean the
Higgs particle gives such and such a
mass are the first class of particles
which cannot have a mass unless the
spontaneous symmetry breaking are the
analogs of the photons the gauge bosons
so tonight I'm going to try to show you
how the photon gets a mass from
spontaneous symmetry breaking down
spontaneous symmetry breaking let's
begin with a boson field Phi we did this
last time but since since it's a subtle
and difficult concept let's do it again
and Phi is a complex field that means
there's a five star to go along with Phi
and we can write Phi in two ways by real
plus I Phi imaginary what does it
correspond to it comes
and what I would do before I real fire
imaginary all we can write it as Phi
equals Rho e to the I alpha where Rho is
the distance along here it's not a real
distance in space at the distance in
field space and alpha is the angle two
different ways polar coordinates and
Cartesian coordinates for the field now
are incidentally five-star is of course
Phi real minus I Phi imaginary and it's
also equal this one here is also equal
to Rho e to the minus I alpha Rho and
alpha are functions of position this is
a field so these are functions of
position and as you can see in either
case there are two fields the real field
and imaginary field or the radial field
and the angular field you might begin to
guess about the connection between Rho
alpha and the two kinds of motions that
can take place here alpha corresponds to
exciting the angular modes if you vary
alpha from place to place
it's like varying around the circle if
you vary Rho it's like moving radially
back and forth which one do you think
gets a mass Rho which one doesn't get a
mass alpha which one is the higgs-boson
Rho which one is the Goldstone boson
alpha good you got it you that's that I
hardly have to go through the
mathematics now no no really
that's the mathematics is now the the
the trick in going through the
mathematics is to write the lagrangian
for this field it's derivative of v star
times the derivative of phi this of
course means time derivative squared
minus space derivative squared but I'll
just write it that way derivative of Phi
with respect to space and time as for
vectors dotted into each other that's
the gradient terms in the energy and you
can work them out in terms of Phi and
Phi star I'll tell you where they are
this becomes derivative of Phi real
squared plus derivative of Phi imaginary
squared in other words it just behaves
as if there were two independent fields
real and imaginary or we can write it in
terms of Rho and alpha and this would
become I'll write it down for you you
can work it out yourself derivative of
Rho squared and then plus Rho squared
times the derivative of alpha squared
Rho is the magnitude of the field alpha
is the angle but each of these are
fields and this is what Lagrangian is
you can either think of it in one way or
the other no problem now let's add in a
potential energy the potential energy
I'm going to assume is symmetric
symmetric with respect to rotations in
this plane in other words that it really
does have a u 1 symmetry for a potential
energy to have a u 1 symmetry it means
it's only a function of Rho equivalently
it's only a function of Phi star Phi it
does not depend on the angle so let's
write that plus V of Rho that also
corresponds well okay
vr Rho let's take actually the potential
always comes in with a minus sign in the
Lagrangian so let's put it in with a
minus sign a simple case would be Rho
squared an energy which increases
quadratically away from the origin
that's a possibility let's think about
that possibility Rho squared it's not
really what I it's a possible Express
um what would that correspond to in
terms of 5real and Phi imaginary just
Rho squared Phi real squared plus Phi
imaginary squared that's the Pythagorean
theorem Rho squared is five real squared
plus Phi imaginary squared so if the
potential was the very simple form of
quadratic we would add here Phi real
squared or minus subtract not important
Phi real squared plus Phi imaginary
squared notice Lagrangian would actually
be the sum of two terms
one for Phi real and one for Phi
imaginary and both of them would have a
mass term there could be a coefficient
here M Squared over 2 let's say then you
will have this situation which I drew
over here where both directions of
oscillation correspond to a mass and
they're quite independent of each other
they don't even couple to each other
they really talk to each other just two
separate fields one that I label Phi
real the other one I label Phi imaginary
now there could be more complicated
things here which would couple them
together but this is the basic picture
if the potential looks like this but
what if the potential looks like this
that's also a function of Rho but it
would be inconvenient to represent it in
terms of fire we landfire imaginary
especially since the minimum is stuck
out here away from the origin the
coordinates Firewheel and phi imaginary
are not obviously the best coordinates
when you stuck out here better
coordinates are the angular coordinate
and the radial coordinate
why because they correspond to two
different kinds of oscillations with two
different frequencies in other words
just think of this as a function of Rho
and alpha now this potential energy
doesn't depend on alpha at all okay but
it does depend on Rho it depends on Rho
in a way which is minimized when Rho is
equal to F
and in fact it takes a good deal of
energy to displace it away from F so
it's natural to write that row what's
it's natural to write that row is equal
to F plus a bit of fluctuation in other
words the minimum energy is when Rho is
stuck at F anyways along here Rose stuck
at F but you can displace it a little
bit and let's represent that
displacement away from F by a letter of
the alphabet and I'm going to choose the
next letter of the alphabet after F
which is h h4 what h figs okay
h4 eggs so the Higgs field is just the
displacement of the radial direction or
the radial part of the field away from
its equilibrium all right now
it caused a good deal of energy to
excite this Higgs field why because it's
got a potential in that potential might
be rather sharp in fact it is rather
sharp so um to some approximation some
rather good approximation we may say
that the low energy behavior is as if
Rho were frozen at value F now this is a
very common thing in physics to say that
there are low energy excitations low
energy oscillations of a system low
frequency oscillations and high
frequency oscillations and ignore the
high frequency oscillations that would
be equivalent to ignoring H here just
saying Rho is equal to F plus something
that takes too much energy for us to
worry about today we'll worry about it
another day when our accelerators have
more energy okay what would this look
like then well Rho is stuck at F we
might as well ignore its derivative okay
more what about V of Rho V of Rho is
just V of F so V is stuck at the minimum
if it's stuck at the minimum it doesn't
doesn't vary from place to place this
and this are irrelevant to the dynamics
of the angular field furthermore since
it costs so much energy to make a bit of
H we can just approximately say that Rho
is equal to F and we find that for the
low energies for the small energy
excitations that the Lagrangian is just
F squared a number times the derivative
of alpha squared there is no potential
energy associated with alpha why is it
no potential energy associated with
alpha for the obvious reason that we
don't gain any potential energy when we
go around the angular direction all
right we this is a little bit less
familiar because it has this F in it but
we could redefine the field we could
redefine the field by inventing a new
field call it beta beta is equal to F
times alpha it's just a rescaling of the
field just a redefinition and then we
would rewrite this as just the Alpha
that's already beta squared
no mass term no mass term because it
doesn't cost any energy to displace the
field homogeneous ly everywhere no mass
term and so alpha or beta depending on
which you want to write is a massless
field it is the Goldstone boson and as I
said what its energy corresponds to is
slow variations of the fields you vary
the field from place to place slowly you
get a little bit of energy if you vary
it slowly enough you get a little bit of
energy from the derivative terms here
but no potential energy so that's the
hallmark of a massless particle and it's
the Goldstone boson
Goldstone bosons are the massless
particles which are the consequences of
the spontaneous symmetry breaking of a
continuous symmetry okay that's the
buzzwords ah that's half the story
that's the spontaneous symmetry breaking
half together with the Goldstone boson
phenomenon the other half of the story
which also has to do with varying the
phase of a field from point to point is
the gauge invariance so I want to spend
a little bit of time I'm going to give
you a break for a few minutes then we're
going to review again what I told you
last time about gauge invariants that
should take us another 15 20 minutes or
10 minutes I'm not sure and then put the
two of them together and see what comes
out okay and what will come out will be
that the Goldstone boson is eaten by the
gauge boson giving the Higgs boson a
mass no giving giving the Higgs boson a
mass and also giving the gauge boson
embarrass ya cuz I'm confused whether
Rho is the radius in the complex plane
or is the field that at a radius in the
complex I know the field is a point in
the complex plane the value that a field
takes on is a point in the complex plane
at every point in space the field has a
value which is the complex point in the
plane
in other words at one point in space the
field is three plus I times or six and
another point in the plane that's pi
plus I times e someplace else it's uh
the Euler macaroni number plus so I
times the small of its number explain
that is except we said instead what's
radially symmetric now the value of the
field at a point is not radially
symmetric the value of the field at a
point is the value of the field at a
point it's not radially symmetric it's
the point on the complex plane what's
radially symmetric is the potential
energy the potential energy is only a
function of this squared plus this
squared three six the field at some
point has the value over there at some
other point in space the field takes on
the value over here some other point it
takes on the value over here the
potential energy is only a function of
the size of the square but 3 + i6 if the
value of the field and ink doesn't say
anything about where an accomplished a
had occurred through 3
the value of the field in X plus iy is
not a sin the value at X plus iy the
value of the field is x and y are not
positions of space this is not the field
at the point x and y this is the field
whose value is a point in the complex
but it's an abstract idea fields or
fields can be complex they can be real
they can be multi-component you can
assemble them together if they have two
components into a into a complex
variable so the field itself is a
complex variable it's a complex variable
where as you move around in space the
field takes on different values on this
complex plane get used to that idea
fields don't just have to be numbers
they can be complex numbers they can be
multi-ball start pushing is innocent
where oh yeah make sure they're going in
the mass hold Russian
if you give it a big enough displacement
won't or go into the other
yah-yah-yah means you're too hard on
pickleball in our swing around
it's just that manifest itself well the
problem is that the amount of energy
that would be involved for the Higgs
field is way beyond the energy that that
even a big accelerator can so it's it's
out of the ballpark from even the LHC
but yes I mean in principle you could
give the give the feel to get big enough
knock to knock it over the top not
everywhere simultaneously in space that
would be an enormous amount of energy
but in some reason yeah but is that
exactly in line with the peak of the day
I want to go off and wind up all right
so it's very unlikely right that's
that's right yeah I would make a bit
would make a monstrous splash of some
kind going off and on let's take out
let's take a 10-minute break okay let's
get let's go through again what we mean
by a field as a function of space and
what this idea of a field which is a
complex variable is just to make it
clear once more we have space x y&z
right all right now we can have fields
in space let's say scalar fields you can
have a scalar field in space which now
what characterizes it as being a scalar
it means it doesn't change when you
rotate coordinates that's all it means
it doesn't change not when you rotate
the coordinates we're talking about here
when you talk rotate the coordinates of
real space it doesn't change that's what
a scalar field is now you can have
several scalar fields let's say in
particular you can have two scalar
fields let's give them names let's call
them Phi I and Phi are the two scalar
fields are you can then assemble them if
you like
this is totally a matter of convention
it's totally a choice it's a useful
Jois it's one of these things in
mathematics which sometimes are really
just useful conventions and this is one
of them in fact the whole idea of
complex numbers is a useful convention
it's a useful convention for
representing pairs of numbers that's all
and the pairs of numbers are called the
real and imaginary parts of the numbers
X not a little bit a column X X stands
for space okay but just real and
imaginary our components are just ways
of speaking about pairs of real numbers
now it is a little more than pairs of
real numbers more structure that goes
into the into the complex numbers but
you know fundamentally it's a way of
talking about pairs of numbers you can
plot pairs of numbers on the Cartesian
plane the Cartesian plane is not real
space it's just a Cartesian plane in
which you've plotted the real and
imaginary parts of complex numbers if I
had two fields two scalar fields one of
which I called Phi real and the other
that's its name if I real and Phi
imaginary I can assemble them together
into a complex field yeah a complex
field and at each point of space there
would be a high real and if I imaginary
okay at each point of space I could go
and plot the value of the field on the
complex plane keep in mind the complex
plane is not space it's just an
auxiliary construction an auxiliary
construction which is useful in
replacing two real fields by one complex
symbol until it is it's a trick for
representing for cutting down the number
of equations that you write cutting it
in half basically by writing him as
equations for complex variables okay so
in that language you would say that the
scalar field the complex scalar field
I is that just that it's a complex
scalar field and at every point in space
real space it has a value that value is
not a single number it's a pair of
numbers why because it's a pair of
fields to begin with that pair of
numbers can be plotted so at this point
of so at this point of space over here
the field is over here at that point of
space the field is over here at that
point that's over here and so forth
that's the idea of a complex scalar
field sometimes the real and imaginary
parts are called the real and imaginary
components of the field but don't get
those confused with the components of a
vector field or a tensor field or the
components of a the gravitational field
those components have to do with
projections onto real space-time
coordinates this has to do with the
projections onto this fictitious
two-dimensional plane that's useful for
writing pairs of numbers now once you
realize that you can write the field as
a complex variable and plot it on the
two-dimensional plane like that then it
becomes a possible symmetry of nature or
possible symmetry of mathematics to
rotate the field in other words there
might be a symmetry which says that you
can real Abel or redefine Phi I and Phi
are by rotation and that happens when
there's when we have lagrangian's like
this which don't change when you do what
when you multiply Phi by e to the I
times of phase these are the class of
lagrangian's which don't change when
you're multiple when you rotate the
fields simultaneously everywhere in
space when you rotate it in this
fictitious plane in other words take the
field at every point of space and you
rotate its value you give a new value to
the field which is related to the old by
changing the angle here rigidly
everywhere in space then this Lagrangian
does not change we went through that
last
time and that's the basic idea of a
complex field with a symmetry with the
symmetry of called u 1 symmetry it's a
global symmetry that's called a global
symmetry a global symmetry is one way
you're not allowed to change the phase
angle in space in space you just rotate
it everywhere yep
so you can see that symmetry just by
looking at where what's a function of R
oh yeah well you can look at it in a
number of ways you can see that since
this has real squared plus imaginary
squared things in it when everything is
a function of real squared plus some and
this one yeah right right so this is a
function of Rho also you can see it here
incidentally what does the symmetry
operation do on Rho and alpha Rho stays
the same and alpha you shift it by a
constant namely the angle that you're
rotating the field by well shifting
alpha by a constant doesn't change its
derivatives right that's correct
right so all right now I think we have
the basic idea now let's go through
again all right now um yes let's go
through the idea of a gauge
transformation we went to it last time
so I'm just going to remind you we're
not going to spend a lot of time on it
and do as fast as we can but please ask
questions
it is not a symmetry of this Lagrangian
to multiply the field Phi by an
arbitrary function of position by an
arbitrary phase this is called a phase e
to the I times this times Phi of X of X
this is not a symmetry we went through
this last time we rewrote that
Lagrangian in terms of Phi Prime and
found out that it didn't have the same
form in other words the Lagrangian
written up there in particular the term
derivative of Phi star times the
derivative of Phi I don't have to put in
the indices mu here you know about that
that is not the same as the derivative
of Phi prime star derivative of v prime
not the same and therefore it is not a
symmetry okay
this is not a symmetry why that's
because when the derivatives act they
act not only on Phi but they act on
theta here they act on theta if theta is
variable if they didn't vary in space
then this would be a symmetry but if
theta varies in space it's not we work
that out in detail last time and I'll
show you in a moment what we found but
to make it a symmetry you have to add
another field a kind of compensating
field a compensating field that will
compensate for the changes in the
Lagrangian when you shift the phase of
the field ah keep in mind it's useful to
remember that shifting the phase of the
field is just adding a function to alpha
ok shifting the phase of the field is
adding a function Phi of X a dur of X to
alpha
it changes the phase angle Everywhere's
by amount theta right if theta is a
constant that's symmetry if theta is not
a constant it's not a symmetry in order
to make it a symmetry you have to add
another field and the other field is
called the vector potential it's a four
vector it has an index mu it's also a
function of position out of it you build
the electromagnetic field E and be your
electric and magnetic field the
transformation property when you do a
gauge transformation like this is called
the gauge transformation
in when you do a gauge transformation
you have to do something to a at the
same time in fact you have to take a
prime of X and set it equal to a of X
plus or minus I always get confused by
the signs here
I think it's plus the derivative this is
a mu of theta in other words you add to
a the gradient the space-time gradient
of theta if you do these two operations
together and you construct the right
kind of Lagrangian it will be invariant
under this operation if it's invariant
it's a symmetry so let me remind you how
it works
Oh incidentally oh that's good enough
hmm you're the mind is the list yeah Oh
rest of our minds I think I think the
idea is that a goes to a prime plus D mu
hey I'm just saying if you write it with
an arrow notation of the transformation
going from starting with a new and going
to what then you have a minus sign if
you don't if you write the
transformation as hey you goes to a new
plus D mu hmm okay then when you write
it in the eighth okay yeah yeah it's
just reading it the other way yeah right
all right but this is the transformation
that you make these are the prime
variables these are the unprimed and I
may have written it the opposite way
last time I don't remember but I will
compensate for any mistakes and not many
mistakes but any change of notation by
changing it consistently everywhere from
one week to another I don't remember the
precise notation but both of them you
know you can do it either way
equals del - del plus I a and D star
equals del - I a I may have changed I
may have inadvertently changed notation
but as long as you do it consistently
everywhere as it's fine okay so let's
now we've seen that the ordinary
derivative of Phi prime is not simply
related to the ordinary derivative of
Phi let's write out the relationship
let's take the derivative of Phi prime
derivative with respect to any axis I'll
stop writing muse and news the
derivative of Phi prime is first of all
equal to e to the I theta which is a
function of x times the derivative of
Phi if that's all there was and we did
multiply the derivative of the complex
conjugate of Phi by the derivative of
Phi the e to the I theta is we cancel
out right all right so if that's all
there was we'd be in fine shape we would
say there's a symmetry but there's
another term and the other term is Phi
times the derivative I times the
derivative of theta all times also e to
the I theta that's this term here which
is the nuisance if all there was was
something which carried and if theta
only entered through e to the I theta
here it would cancel out when we
multiply this by the complex conjugate
but theta comes into its derivative over
here that's the problem
okay all right to fix that problem
why should you want to fix it well it's
a fact of nature that there is a gauge
that there are gauge symmetries
that's also an interesting fact of
mathematics that such symmetries are
possible to make it possible you replace
the ordinary derivative by what's called
the covariant derivative this is a
mathematical concept that comes from the
theory of fiber bundles but I think it
was I don't know whether the theory of
fiber bundles was invented before or
after the notion of gauge invariance in
physics I have a feeling it was invented
afterwards but someone that's right I
think so yeah right I don't know but I
don't know what the mathematicians
invented it completely independently
through the value but I really don't
know in any case it is both a
mathematical and a physical concept and
in order to make the Lagrangian gauge
invariant you invent the new kind of
derivative it's called the covariant
derivative with respect to again with
respect to each direction of space or
time you write that this is equal to the
ordinary derivative
I think it's plus now I'm going to get
myself confused I'll try plus if it
doesn't work we'll change it plus I
times a times v now there is an implicit
index in here once more I will write it
just the number a is a vector derivative
plus multiplying by a sometimes this is
indicated by saying that derivative is
replaced by derivative plus I a but it
only makes sense if you apply it to a
complex field like Phi so this is the
definition of the covariant derivative
and if I were to write the covariant
derivative of Phi star it is by
definition just the complex conjugate so
it's equal to D mu Phi star
- I a mu five-star okay now I assert
easy to check is it a check that the
relationship between the covariant
derivative of five and the covariant
derivative of Phi prime is very simple
all you have to do is evaluate the
covariant derivative of what is the code
this is the covariant derivative of Phi
look let's write down with the covariant
derivative of Phi prime is well it's
exactly the same except you stick
Prime's Everywhere's D mu Phi prime is
just equal to D mu Phi plus I a prime
times Phi Phi Prime Thank You Phi Prime
everywhere is Phi prime v prime okay if
you stick Phi prime over here you're
going to wind up with this extra term
over here as if I were if I evaluate D
mu Phi Prime let me write it better be
mu Phi prime here it is let's see is
this right no what did I do here this
was D mu Phi prime right hmm five five
zero five no no no
yeah no no there's no difference between
capital and not capital so Greg unifies
are actually lowercase and when you use
the bars they are uppercase come
when you don't use the bars they're
lowercase footmark spies or cases hard
if you don't have them keep the I I bars
on the top and the bottom finds lower
case sorry we're tonight bar you know
those bars that you write on the top
yeah like those things upper case fine
yeah I'm just telling you there's no
distinction in my notation between upper
case and lower case sometimes I like to
put those little things there when I'm
when I'm feeling in a good mood I put
these things on when I'm not feeling in
a good mood I leave them out I see so in
most of the books they use lower case
yeah
but then for special cases no no okay
I'm Phi is Phi Phi is Phi and I have not
them and I did not mean to distinguish
up a case from lower case right wait
wait wait I got to put in all this to
mean I want to be consistent here what
let me swear oh okay no was there a
questions he was asking about indices
balancing oh I don't remember my stuff
wrote it by for refuge do we need an
index up index down yeah
yeah what's really meant by D no Phi
star D mu no no no no no no no no they
are the okay so let's if you have a
four-vector an arbitrary for vector V mu
you can multiply it by G mu nu a
symmetric and get V mu we know all right
the meaning of this symbol for ordinary
special relativity is that the time
components of these two are the same in
sign and the space components are
opposite all right so
right the meaning of this is it should
be taken to be the upper to the lower
the covariant vector times the earth
right but I don't want to write that
every time over and over so I just write
an abstract symbol derivative times
derivative yeah the lowering operator
there hmm
you have lower on the left upper on the
right sorry you're right thank you right
but we've already gone through special
relativity a number of times and so I
don't feel the need to to be so careful
about relativity indices all right so I
won't even I won't even bother writing
them for the most part I'm not going to
write them I keep writing them okay
ah good now here I if i plug in D mu Phi
Prime I will get this unwanted nasty
piece over here but if I also plug in a
prime times Phi where is a prime let me
write a prime over here a prime equals a
see the plus or minus D mu theta then
they will cancel they will cancel there
will be a term D I D nu theta times Phi
you know what I mean right so if I the
to D mu Thetas will cancel each other
one from calculating a derivative here
and the other from the explicit
difference between a prime and AE so
what will I find what I'll tell you
exactly what I will find I will find
that D mu Phi Prime this one over here
is equal not quite to just D mu Phi what
are missing
each of the I theta overall eetu the I
theta so you say well I didn't get any
where's D mu of Phi Prime is not the
same as D mu Phi it's not gauge
invariant true enough but only
difference from being gauge invariant by
an outside overall factor of e to the I
theta which will disappear when you
multiply this by its conjugate notice
that in this formula here the derivative
of theta does not appear you have the
covariant derivative of Phi prime is
equal to the covariant derivative of Phi
up to this overall factor of e to the I
theta which will cancel when you
multiply this by D mu of Phi star prime
that will be equal to e to the minus I
theta times D mu of Phi star so when you
multiply these two together the unwanted
unpleasant things that have derivatives
of theta in them disappear what is the
cost the cost is you had to introduce a
new field which transformed in this way
which in this way over here
but once you allow yourself that freedom
to introduce a new field the vector
potential then this Lagrangian over here
becomes invariant than the gauge
transformations later on we'll write it
out in some more detail but one more
point before we jump to the conclusion
and that's the electromagnetic part of
the Lagrangian this field is a charge
carrying field it's not the electron
because the electron is not a boson but
it could be some charged boson of some
sort okay
some charged boson of some sort
and there are charge bosons a helium
atom is a helium nucleus as a charge
boson so if I represent some charge
boson a represents the vector potential
and the electromagnetic field is also
governed by a Lagrangian the Lagrangian
is defined f nu nu equals D nu a mu
minus D nu a mu the space-time the mixed
space-time component is the electric
field the space space component are the
magnetic fields and the square of F now
that there are some signs that go into
it f mu nu F mu nu that's a squared
minus B squared that's the lagrangian
area of the electromagnetic field the
important thing for us is that this is
gauge invariant this does not change
when you make a gauge transformation
what happens to a a changes by the
gradient of theta so what happens to
this F prime becomes f plus the nu D nu
theta minus the nu nu theta these two
terms cancel so f is itself gauge
invariant and when you add F squared
it's still gauge invariant so the whole
upshot is oh one more thing one more
thing you can add that's gauge invariant
and that's a potential which depends
only on Phi star Phi II a potential
which depends only on Phi star Phi so
the full Lagrangian of a simple gauge
Theory involving the interaction of
electromagnetism with a charged scalar
field would look like this
it would have D mu Phi D mu let's just
for D Phi D Phi star it would have
viii of five star Phi which is just V of
Rho if you remember and then plus F
squared plus a squared minus B squared
and it would be fully gauge invariant no
change in it when you make a CH
transformation that's the simplest gauge
theory in a nutshell that's basically it
that's basically the structure of all
gauge theories they have a structure
similar to this now let's ask how what
happens when the symmetry of rotation of
Phi is spontaneously broken when does
that happen it happens when the
potential has this upside-down sombrero
I guess it's not an upside-down sombrero
when it has that shape so that the
ground state of Phi breaks the symmetry
what happens what new thing happens or
what new thing happens oh before we do
that let's let's just remember that the
this potential is such that the angular
Direction is a Goldstone boson no mass
the radial direction which we call the
Higgs boson has a mass and furthermore
the photon does not have a mass how do I
know the photon doesn't have a mass the
reason is simple the F is only a
function of the derivatives of the
vector potential that means if you were
to shift the vector potential everywhere
simultaneously there would be no change
in energy okay
shift the pretend the vector potential
everywhere is together no change in
energy that means a massless particle so
there are two massless two apparent
massless particles floating around in
this theory one is the Goldstone boson
and the other is the is the photon
and now watch what happens let's take a
what way what would a mass term for the
photon look like if you had one well the
mass term is always something which is
quadratic in the field for example the
mass of Phi if it existed would be Phi
star Phi star Phi or Phi squared 5 5 X
Phi real squared plus Phi imaginary
squared or the photon mass B it would be
something proportional to a squared to
the vector potential squared if you
allowed yourself to put the vector
potential squared into the Lagrangian
you would have a mass for the photon
that would not be gauge invariant look
at it
here's a squared which means this means
a mu a mu if you put that into the
Lagrangian what would happen when you
make a gauge transformation it would
shift to a plus the gradient of theta
squared all right
but that's not the same as a squared a
squared is not the same as a plus
derivative of theta squared so a squared
just a squared a squared would not be
gauge invariant would not be gauge
invariant so a mass term is not allowed
by gauge invariance gauge invariance is
a symmetry which prohibits the photon
from having a mass or does it well let's
look at this little engine a little more
closely and in particular let's look at
this term over here
in fact let's concentrate on the
Goldstone boson piece of it and we can
do that by writing that Phi is f times e
to the I at now let's not let's not
let's just let's go for it here's the
here's the terminal again G all right so
what's in here D Phi is derivative of
Phi plus there's a plus I a times Phi is
that right hmm that's what I wrote d Phi
star is derivative of Phi minus I a five
star all right now let's suppose that
we're looking at the ground state when
the field is right over here when Phi is
equal to F let's say just the real value
the real value of Phi is equal to F
let's for simplicity let's say the
imaginary part of Phi is zero so the
field is sitting right over here let's
look at the various terms first of all
ah well the most important term is this
one here a times five times five star
but five times five star is stuck at the
minimum here
it's stuck at the minimum because it
takes a lot of energy to shift Phi away
from the minimum so as long as we don't
excite a lot of energy is an effective
term in the Lagrangian which is just a
squared times Phi star Phi which is just
equal to F squared times a squared right
somebody said yeah why'd you say from
because you immediately see that this is
behaving like a mass term for the photon
this is behaving exactly like a mass
term for the photon what's the mass the
mass is basically just F actually twice
f well square root of two times F but
this factor this numerical factor here
is playing the role forget this that's
playing the role of a squared times s
squared which would be a mass for the
photon it would be an energy that you
get when you shift the field homogeneous
li okay so what have we learned we've
learned that when you spontaneously
break the symmetry when you study the
theory in the neighborhood of the
minimum over here the effect of one of
the terms in the Lagrangian is just to
make a mass for the photon isn't that
interesting when the photon propagates
in this world where the symmetry is
spontaneously broken it behaves as if it
had a mass and it does have a mass for
all practical purposes so we've gotten
around the statement that says photons
can't have mass now real photons of
course don't have mass but this photons
in this world where the spontaneously
broken symmetry do have mass the second
thing is the Goldstone boson disappears
why does the Goldstone boson disappear
well let's remember what the Goldstone
boson is is this angle alpha the angle
of the field on the complex plane what
does a gauge transformation of all what
is the Goldstone boson the Goldstone
boson is simply a slowly varying or a
varying value of alpha alpha is a field
it can vary in space if it couldn't vary
in space it wouldn't be interesting
alpha can vary in space but you can make
alpha vary another way you can make it
vary by doing a gauge transformation
adding a little bit of theta of X so you
can make alpha vary from place to place
and you
think that that Lake so Goldstone boson
but it doesn't because this is a
symmetry a symmetry means that you don't
change the energy it means that the
system stays in the ground state this is
not a real change it's a gauge
transformation so the Goldstone boson
completely disappears it completely
disappears it just becomes a gauge
transformation no real energy associated
with it and at the same time the vector
potential gains a mass so it's a sort of
zero-sum game you get rid of one man
where you fill another zero-sum game
you've removed the massless Goldstone
boson and we move the massless photon
replacing the massless photon by a
massive photon and at the same time the
Higgs boson now has a mass because it
oscillates about here that's the that's
the big phenomenon it by plugging in
basically just by plugging in the value
of the higgs field or the value of Phi
at the minimum here we generated a mass
term for the photon and where did it
come from it came from this covariant
derivative so it just came from the
covariant derivative ah
could you rewrite your whole leg ranging
in size could you rewrite the whole
librarian in those terms yes you can
and you know yes you can you can rewrite
the Lagrangian in those terms you can do
a gauge transformation and basically
completely remove this angular degree of
freedom completely remove the angle from
the I'll show you a little simple baby
version of that if you completely forgot
the radial degree of freedom alt enough
this completely froze it just completely
froze it you would find that the
Lagrangian let's see yeah the covariant
derivative of Phi would become F I think
times the derivative of alpha plus the
vector potential itself maybe times e to
the R
let's see Phi is just equal to F times e
to the I alpha and so the derivative of
Phi is f I alpha sorry fifa15 to the I
alpha so there would be an e to the I
alpha multiplying the whole thing this
is just setting the magnitude or the row
equal to F okay I think F would come on
the outside here wouldn't it if we come
on the outside this would be the
covariant derivative of Phi and it would
contain the derivative of the angular
part that's the important thing it
contains the derivative the angular part
all right what about the derivative of
Phi star that would be the same thing
derivative of alpha I here - I a times e
to the minus I alpha F I'm getting tired
so it's getting
getting a little bit late that's that's
what you would get okay when you
multiply them together you would get
exactly what you expect okay now you
also have F mu nu you have this times
this in the Lagrangian and you have F mu
nu squared now let's make a gauge
transformation this is a clever gauge
transformation which is designed to get
rid of this term all together how can
you make a gauge transformation that
gets rid of this term just set theta
equal to minus alpha remember what
happens to the vector potential when you
make a gauge transformation it just
picks up a derivative theta if you make
your gauge transformation using for the
gauge function theta alpha itself this
just goes away completely or sorry it
doesn't go away completely it just
becomes a and this terminal Lagrangian
just becomes a squared so by design you
can construct the gauge transformation
which just removes this this times this
gets rid of the alpha dependence
altogether and you just get F squared
times a squared all you get is the mass
term that's all that's left and of
course you still have F squared but this
is gauge invariance so it doesn't change
when you do the gauge transformation net
result are the angular degree of freedom
just sort of disappears some magic
happen the angular degree of freedom
disappeared the Goldstone boson is gone
and the photon has a mass meanwhile the
Higgs boson which is this radial
oscillation that's still there so this
is the magic of the Higgs phenomena and
it's the phenomenon of giving a mass to
the gauge bosons by spontaneous emission
is it fair to say that the the
oscillations in alpha are
indistinguishable from just gauge
oscillations problem yes from this
station yes that's fair to say it's not
only fair to say it's true now I will
tell you right now that this is also the
physics of superconductors in a
superconductor
there are charged bosons the charged
bosons are bound pairs of electrons
they're called Cooper pairs Cooper pairs
are bound are loosely bound pairs of
electrons but they are bosons so there's
a charged boson field in the system and
the charged boson field gets shifted
away from the origin by some complicated
dynamics in the superconductor it
creates a condensate of those charged
pairs and it's equivalent to exactly
this kind of spontaneous symmetry
breaking where Phi would be replaced by
the field describing the Cooper pairs so
this is also the physics of a
superconductor and in the superconductor
the photon also behaves like a like a
massive particle one last thing how can
you lose a degree of freedom how on
earth can a degree of freedom disappear
the angular dissipative degree of
freedom it didn't disagree at they
disappear what has happened a massless
photon has two polarization States
remember polarization is a little arrow
that there is perpendicular to the
motion of the photon it's if you like
the light of the direction of the
electric field oscillations so every
photon carries with it a a polarization
vector there are two orthogonal
directions for the polarizer if the
photon is going that way the
polarization can be that way or can be
that way so there are two polarization
States you can also think of them as the
states of circular polarization of the
photon there is no state in which the
polarization vector of the photon points
along the direction of motion Maxwell
theory doesn't allow that why is that
assistant if a photon is described as a
vector how can it be that it only has
two components and not a third and the
answer is very simple
the photon moves of the speed of light
it can never be brought to rest suppose
it could be brought to rest supposing
the photon could be brought to rest if
it could be brought to rest and you
brought it to rest it was going down
that way and you brought it to rest that
had a I've had a polarization along the
x-axis and you brought it to rest it
would be a particle at rest with a
polarization along the x-axis
now you could accelerate it along the
x-axis and all of a sudden it would
become a particle whose polarization was
along its direction of motion so the
answer is a if a particle like the
photon were to have mass it would have
to have three directions of polarization
it could have you could bring it to rest
and once it's at rest there's no
distinction between the three directions
it would have to have three directions
of polarization and then if you sped it
up along some axis it would have three
directions of polarization the massless
particle can never be brought to rest
and it's perfectly consistent for it to
only have two directions of polarization
namely circular this way or circular
this way another way of thinking about
it is if you take a particle circularly
right-handed polarized and you brought
it to rest and then accelerate it off in
the opposite direction it would all of a
sudden have left handed polarized it
would have left hand left hand so it's
also a way to think about it the point
is that you have not lost the degree of
freedom the Goldstone boson has really
become the other missing polarization of
the photon or another way of saying it
is you started with three degree or four
degrees of freedom the to come the two
component for each each focus the two
components of the charged scalar and the
two components of polarization of the
photon in the end you were left again
with four degrees of freedom
three polarizations of the photon and
the Higgs boson so you really haven't
lost any degrees of freedom you've
you've turned the Goldstone boson into
the what's called the longitudinal
degree of freedom of the photon the one
in which the vector potential or a field
is pointing the vert the electric field
is pointing along the direction of
motion that's what's happening but they
all have mass now the next time I will
show you the physics in a simplified
context the same context of why the
fermions the electrons and the and the
quarks get their mass from the Higgs
phenomenon so far we haven't talked
about the quarks and the electrons they
also have mass what does the matter what
does their mass have to do with the
Higgs phenomenon that will be the next
time when we finish that we will have a
setup in which all particles including
the Higgs boson all get their mass from
the same place namely the spontaneous
symmetry breaking then we can start to
talk about this very interesting
situation that all of the particles in
nature that we know you know that we've
measured are the ones which would become
massless if there was no spontaneous
symmetry breaking boy that I've had
enough for the night
for more please visit us at stanford.edu